"Foundries Makedonia"
Panos Karagiannakidis
Michail Arbazoglou
Thessaloniki
This is where you'll lay your dust!
Here! You punks! You gypsy-dog iron smiths!
Animal control will get to you eventually, you clowns!
Swedish girls, aged fifteen to eighteen.
From their mom's breast straight to consumption.
Marika will straighten you out. Start with the washing.
Speedboat-rides under the moonlight.
Boo, you herdsman!
Here we'll erect your grave! Here we'll erect your grave!
Come on, let's go.
- I'm coming Thasos. I'm coming...
...fish, oregano, oil and lemon sauce, boiled lobster...
...two meter long breams. This big!
Morons!
- Boo!
- Bye, you fools!
- Bye, farewell!
The Makedonian summer comedy...
Let the Women Wait
- Tell me, want us to stay in Kavala today and move towards Kara Orman?
...there, I can fish for something and I'll take care of you too.
- That is not possible, Panos...
- Why?
- Because Antonis is waiting. You know what
he told me on the phone?
"You laid three families on me and you are enjoying your freedom in Thessaloniki."
- Why didn't you tell him...
..."you hillbilly. You Peloponessian dirtbag.
Each time you are seperate with Eleni"...
..."don't we have to put up with her along with your kids and your mother?"
- I didn't tell him Panos because he is right.
You know how hard it is to take
nine kids to the beach each day...
...to shop for sixteen people,
to take the seniors to the swings?
- He takes the seniors to the swings?!
- Along with the kids.
Of course, the seniors don't swing but they enjoy watching
and during the evening they want to have hamburgers at the square.
If it was me, I would have killed someone.
- Let him kill his mother!
You know what she told me on Easter when I cut some kokoretsi for her?
"Come to Padaditsa and see
how real kokoretsi tastes like."
- Indeed, in Papaditsa the kokoretsi is out of this world.
- Out of this world?
You know what a professional from Kalamata told me?
I ask him...
..."How come Mr. Marmatzeas is the kokoretsi in Padaditsa so delicious?"...
...And he replies tete a tete...
..."Because in Papaditsa they don't wash the entrails".
- That means we are eating...
- Grilled shit with mustard and pepper...
...that's what we are eating!
Because...
...look at what God did.
He creates three sisters.
I take the first, all right.
You take the next. All right.
And then comes he during the PASOK pre-congress...
...And marries the youngest.
- That's how we became brothers-in-law.
- Yes! But, what have I ever done...
...to become family with an alderman
from Papaditsa, Lakonia?
Don't stop...
Stop. Stop!
Sir, I'm afraid we made a mistake.
How may I help you?
It is human to err.
I was told that, in order to reach Kavala...
...the sea must be on my right.
And where is the sea?
On my left.
Is that your dad?
Your heading is correct...
...when you reach Asprovalta, the sea will be on your right...
...this is lake Volvi.
Have you ever bathed in the Lake?
- No.
Under the moonlight, the nymphs emerge.
- It must be magical.
- Magic...
- This must certainly be the place where the historical Volvi Congress took place...
- I'm not sure.
- They say that, this congress was a watershed...
...and influenced the political scene.
- Maybe.
- I thank you nevertheless.
We should come one evening...
...Mister?
Panagiotis. My friends call me "Panos".
...Mr. Panos told me
...that, under the full moon the nymphs emerge...
...and bathe in the water.
Again, I thank you.
You see what God does?
Creating creatures like that
and then unleashing them upon the world.
And He does not care if He takes my breath away.
So, what do I do now?
It came as a bit of a suprise, Panos...
...But until we reach the ferry,
we'll have forgotten all about her.
Well, I'm not forgetting her!
Time is a doctor, Panos. He passes and he obscures everything.
Now you must preoccupy yourself with other things
and remove her from your thoughts.
Get out of my thought...
...everything that is you hurts...
...since you are living with someone else.
I don't need anything...
...what are you looking for anymore...
...and are still torturing me?
Get out of my head...
...the wounds are not enough for you...
...that I touch and it hurts...
...Get out of my head.
Get out! Get out! Get out!
Get out of my head...
...the wounds are not enough for you...
...that because of you I count...
Get out of my head...
Get out! Get out! Get out!
- Panos, I think it would be better if we drank our coffee in Kavala.
- I'll drink it wherever I want to drink it!
And if someone calls saying we are late
I will also have something to say about his momma.
Good day.
Something's on your mind.
Didn't you get what happened?
The girl tells him "let's come
during a full moon night"...
..."the Sir told me", while pointing at me...
...and I say "Panagiotis"...
..."My friends call me Panos"...
...and the girl says...
..."Mr. Panos told me..."...
You got it?
- Get what?
-Get what?! She didn't say "Mr. Panagiotis"...
...she said "Mr. Panos".
- Are you getting it now?
-No.
Doesn't matter. Because he got it.
...and when he hears "Mr. Panos told me"...
...he thinks to himself "this is getting serious"
and he steps on the gas pedal and zooms away.
Indeed, he left in a hurry.
So, think first, understand, and then say
"I don't understand"!
Frappé, ice cold, two spoons of sugar.
The same, no sugar.
Panos, Frappé with no sugar is poison.
I'll do whatever I want!
Don't say a word...
...just let me go...
- We are listening to the same song.
- Of course.
And he knows we are listening to the same song.
Who Panos?
...empty words that you are used to saying.
...and don't speak...
- Excuse me.
- Good day.
- Good day...
...is this a radio?
CD.
...don't tell me, don't tell me...
...that you'll rebuild what you destroyed...
Don't speak, don't speak...
...only with words...
Panos?
She shows herself, right?
And she tells me, let's go...
...and it's like my life restarts.
Panos...
...I'm picturing the girl coming
and telling you "let's go"...
...do you put her in the truck
and you go?
And she gets black from the filth
from head to toe?
Why aren't you answering?
- Because, I'm waiting to see
where you are getting with this.
- I'm not trying to get anywhere...
...I'm just making logical assumptions.
You are going to have to buy a new car.
Not a Mercedes...
...but certainly a convertible.
Ten million.
Where are you going to take her?
Are you going to rent a tiny room in Thasos?
Of course not.
A suite in Porto Carras.
In the evening she will want to go to the casino.
...and if she is on a streak, OK.
But if not?
Are you the one to tell her "play prudently" or will you tell her "go on, I got you"?
I'll tell her "go on, I got you".
And then summer is over...
...and for the winter you go to Thessaloniki...
...you will rent a penthouse in Panorama for her...
...and you will eat in the fine restaurants.
You have left a wife and three kids a sick sister and an old father behind you.
They are hungry...
...and you are eating in Pringkiponisos...
...and suddenly you see Fotoula and Dionisakis...
...and they are begging at the tables...
...What do you do at that moment?
- I throw a rope and hang myself!
This girl must come from around Phaliro or Glyfada
and you take her with on Sunday
on a match against Olympiacos...
...and Ivić dives in the penalty area,
and the Anchovies shout for a penalty shot...
...and she is shouting for a penalty too.
What will you do in front of the PAOK fans, lifelong fan?
- I kill her!
I know you, that is why I theorize.
And, to come back to economical matters...
...what will you do when the car payments are due...
...the bouncing checks from the boutiques, the jewelry stores,
the night clubs, the florists, the restaurants?
The girl herself, to save you will say
"Panos, that's it for us".
And you, hurt, alone, one morning you will
present yourself to the prosecutor.
The sentence will be fifteen years,
this being your first offense.
One morning the gate will open and you will exit the prison.
You will look down towards Thessaloniki.
Your children will be rehabilitated.
Marika will be living with someone else.
Your father is dead and your sister is
incarcerated in some asylum.
And you will walk down to the White Tower...
...you will take a stroll but no one
will welcome you or greet you.
Because, people do not forgive those who
due to love have fallen!
- Oh, my God!
- Panos! Panos!
Panos, what in God's name did you do?!
Miss, your name?
- Clytemnestra.
- Ms. Clytemnestra, this same thing...
...has happened to him two more times in the past.
- He trows himself in the lake?
No, in the sea. Once in the Messiniakos and
once in the Pagasitikos bays.
- For the same reason?
- For... a similar reason.
Let him drink a bitter coffee and take a warm shower and
then I'll take his blood-pressure, OK?
Thank you a lot.
Panos, sometimes we wonder
"for which of our sins did God create women?"
But, I'm thinking now,
a woman destroyed you...
...but it is also women who saved you.
We wish for you always to be well.
- Always in good health!
- Amen!
- Thank you.
- Farewell.
- Thank you very much.
- Get well soon.
- Thank you.
- Hello.
How are you feeling?
Getting better...
No!
But, the doctoresses told me to drink bitter coffee.
Yeah, that's what they said Panos.
But, when I explained your situation a bit better they said
"better add four spoons of sugar".
- What situation are you talking about exactly?
- Your situation, Panos.
But, instead of telling them about love et cetera,
I told them that sometimes...
...you develop a kind of obstruction in your heart.
- And what did they say?
They were touched.
Of course, they are doctoresses
and they understood about what kind of obstruction I was talking about.
Because one of them said "God, why can't things like that happen to me as well".
- Things like what?
- How should I know? Things...
Drink so your blood sugar goes up a bit, get some strength into you.
- I feel regret.
- No Panos, it's not your fault.
I am paying for my mistakes.
-...Life is at fault for laying out traps for us.
- Because, when he says...
..."I was told, to get to Kavala
the sea must be on my right"...
...I should have told him "that's true, turn back and it will be on your right"...
- Would you direct him the wrong way Panagiotis?
- Of course I would.
He would have reached Platamonas and the girl would have told him...
..."Lakis, the sea is on the left again."
Let's assume his name is Lakis.
He would have gotten out the car, would have asked again and would have been told "turn back my good man"...
..."to go to Kavala the sea must be on your right."
The imbecile would have turned
again and past Thessaloniki...
...at the Volvi lake, the sea would be on his left yet again.
- We should have fooled him like that Panagiotis.
- Yeah, but then you jump in and say...
..."in Asprovalta the sea will be on your right".
Why would you do such a thing?!
- Because, people like us Panagiotis do not
wish evil even to their enemies.
- Well, I do!
Make him travel back and forth from Platamonas to Volvi
half a dozen times until he gets crazy, the fool!
We are nice people. We don't wish evil to anyone
and everyone steps on our throat.
Regret. I feel regret!
I regret it all. I regret it all.
And it's all because of my egoism.
Now, I pay for my mistakes.
I regret it all. I regret it all.
Don't pick up!
Antonis? Panos had a sudden malaise. He was feeling down and
his blood sugar got low. We will be in Kavala...
...in an hour, with the ferry we will be on Thasos at around three or four.
What the hell are you telling him? I could be sitting here with a blood-pressure in the low twenties.
- I'm not going anywhere without a doctor taking a look at me first.
- We can't leave. Yes, there are two doctoresses here.
- What you are saying Antonis? How can you even think of such a thing?!
- What this Arcadian shepherd...
...the Peloponessian dirtbag saying? Is he looking in a mirror?
Explain what Antonis? Someone got lost, we tried to help he and he says...
..."it was here where the historical congress of Volvi took place"...
...and I tell him "I'm not sure". And then Panos got
involved and they started fighting.
Yes Antonis! Because of the congress.
- He won't believe us even if we swear on the Bible.
- What did he tell you?
- He asked me "since when is Panos involved in politics?". And I tell him...
..."politics never gave us anything."
If we don't work there is no PASOK to feed us.
Well said! And you hang up on him too.
I didn't hang up, he did. "Because" he said...
..."I'm not paying for the mobile line to listen to your bullshit".
Filthy mouth! Filth!
- Good day.
- Good day too you.
Lift your right sleeve please.
But... I'm alright.
- The tent turned out nicely, thank you.
- Oh, it was nothing.
You see Miss, I was in the Engineer Corps.
- We would build a bridge in one day.
- One day?
- Yes. And when the army passed,
we would tear it down again.
- Why?
So that the enemy would not pass as well.
- Twelve over eight.
- Your brother in law has the blood pressure of a teenager.
So, you are leaving?
Well, yes. The family is waiting you see.
- Good day.
You got away with it Panos,
but I shouldn't have stopped.
When you saw the girl and yelled "stop"
I should have stepped on the gas.
- As if it was her fault.
- She caused your destabilization.
Get to your senses!
It was he who destabilized me!
Because he wants to trap us. So that we take care of the
seniors while he goes spearfishing.
- Indeed, he might have thought of that.
- Yes, but what he has not thought of
is that I might get crazy...
...and throttle his mommy at the central square.
- Is that radio?
- CD.
- Again, good day to you.
Panos, leave Antonis to God.
We need to get back to our families.
He will sail and he will ask the strangers...
..."have you seen my brothers in law?" And no one will know to tell him.
And he will come back alone, like a dog.
I will destroy his mental health!
- Panos, he will send Marika and Georgia to sail to take revenge.
- Our wives?!
- Yes Panos.
And they will ask the strangers and no one will know to tell them.
And they will go home at midnight and the children will cry...
...and he will laugh in secret and his mental health will be just fine.
- You think he will play us like that?
Panos, Antonis grew up in PASOK, that's like PASOK 101.
But, Panagiotis, sometimes I think he is not that bad...
...he works all day for the Party and at night he sells olive oil...
...and during the weekend he reads.
- Who works like that?
- He cakes up though!
He does cake up but he also lends us a lot and
we always say "you'll get it next month".
- Yeah, so what? Is he not going to get it?
- He is, but we are behind...
...and, we also said to ask for a new loan...
...and we will pay the grand sum.
- Better for him...
...because if he gets it all at once, he will invest it in one place and make an impact.
Small sums have no impact!
One night I went to his office. I saw him, and
you must believe me Panos, I saw him
sitting alone on the chair.
And I thought to myself "this man might be destined for something greater".
It's coming again...
- What is coming Panos?
- The thought of her...
...I'm trying to get her out of my head, but she is coming.
How is it coming Panagiotis?
- I see her in front of me, looking at me.
- Looking at you?
Yes. Now I turn my head...
...and, normally, there should be the lake...
...well, I don't see any lake!
- You can't see the lake!?
There's a whole lake there and you can't see it?!
- No.
- What do you see?
I see her!
Well, that's it! We are going nowhere! You will sleep for five hours at least...
...with Ms. Doctor I will find a nice fish...
...a catfish or a carp...
...and grill it with lemon and oil. You will get up...
...and you will eat to regain your strength and then at dusk...
...we will go find our families.
[SONG] I am chuffed...
Am I chuffed?
- No Mr. Panos.
So?
Michalis.
Yes Panos.
Come every five minutes and check on me.
Why must I come Panagiotis?
To check if I'm still alive.
[SONG] Again, you'll see love as a prison.
And you will wonder about those teary eyes.
Again, you'll leave and run like mad.
Antonis, yes Antonis...
...I called to say the following.
Because, the situation is grave and I can't manage by myself.
We argued because about the Congress, how many times must I tell you?
And we are arguing about the Congress...
...and he has a girl with him. And Panos starts speaking with her...
...and the guy gets mad...
...and he takes her and they leave.
And that cost Panos dearly.
What can I say? Should I say that we are losing him?
And I try, to forget you I try.
There is no place where I can cry.
I must introduce you to an important scientist...
...Professor Petseropoulos, lecturer of Psychology
at the University of Washington.
Nice to meet you.
Mr. Michalis, on behalf of the KAPI of Makedonia and Thrace...
...we congratulate you for fishing a hundred kilos worth of fish.
We ran into a school.
We also congratulate you about the quality of the meal.
We drink towards the rapid restoration of your brother-in-law's health.
We drink towards the good health of the bathers.
Fish!
Right away Panos, it's getting de-boned. You regained
your appetite...
...and that is a
sign that you are getting better.
Don't worry about your relative.
He is just showing symptoms of a simple
impulse control disorder.
- I see...
For example, a man falls in love with a woman...
...will he destroy himself in her charm or will he control the impulse?
He will control the impulse.
Well done! Bravo!
During the first stage, that person will lose his sight.
He does Professor.
Because he says "the lake should be here but I can't see it" and I tell him...
...the lake is right there and you can't see it Panos?
- He can't.
He only sees the face of the woman who is leading him to destruction.
To save himself he must drown her in the lake.
If not her, then any woman.
Dear Lord!
Dr. Sylvia is asking if you are going to use the multiplication-table method.
Exactly.
I will start with with the higher scale of nine-by-nine and I'll go down from there.
If he does not answer three-by-three correctly...
- What happens then Professor?
- Then unfortunately...
- He has a family.
- Let's start from the middle.
Ask him please. Five-by-five.
Panos!
Fish!
But, Mr. Panos.
It's getting de-boned Panos, patience.
Five-by-five?
Forty!
Not good at all.
- Oh God.
- Do not despair.
Four-by-four.
Panos! Four-by-four?
Eighteen!
Better, better. He is getting close.
- A bit better.
- And now...
...the critical three-by-three.
Panos.
Three times three?
Nine!
Thank you! Thank's a lot!
Music! Music!
[SONG] Whoever told you that I learned...
...to live without you is a liar.
I'm living a nightmare. Dreams like wounds.
I bring in my mind all moments...
...where I wanted you to come and see.
Please don't deny me that.
Come and find me.
Just to see...
..how my life is like and feel sorry for me.
Come and find me...
When you got under the van and lifted the bell I thought...
..."This man is taking care of three children
a wife, a father, a sick sister"...
..."me, his friends, PAOK..."
"...and how does life repai him? With breadcrumbs."
...that's what I said.
- Leave me alone.
A day will come when life will be different.
We won't exist until then but that's all right.
It's enough that they will remember us.
They will remember that we were alive once.
Pour him something so that he shuts up.
[SONG] Whoever told you that I learned...
...to live without you is a liar.
Thoughts like stabs in my heart
We will start the business for the women.
If they make their own money they won't pay any attention to us.
And we will live a life we never imagined.
They told me "Psomiadis is sucking you dry" and Eleni said...
..."your children don't have a shirt to change."
- What did Eleni say?!
- She is enabling our women Panos.
Why didn't you say "Antonis is bringing in the dough day and night, how can you be ungrateful?"
I did Panos. And she said "If Antonis had any brains he would not break his back for the Party..."
..."he would be a minister like Tzoumakas."
- Isn't she going to Italy to buy clothes?
- Is Thessaloniki too small to shop in?
And the idiot still pays!
If things were right this man would be sanctified.
Panos, my mind stopped working.
Do you happen to know how much six times six is?
- Thirty-six.
- Seven times seven?
- Fifty-nine.
Come and find me to see how my life is like.
And feel sorry for me.
Come and find me and maybe you will think about...
...how I am dying alone if you don't come back.
How I am dying alone if you don't come back.
How I am dying alone... Come and find me.
Is there a refectory here?
Yes, but it's not open yet.
As you can see, it's dawn and we are alone.
Do you want some music, maybe?
Do you have the "Carmina Burana"?
We have Angela, Kaitoula Garmpi...
No!
Alright. We came early because Mr. Panos...
...wants to hear music the moment he wakes up.
Oh really?
And what kind of music does Mr. Panos request?
He prefers Mr. Melas, Mr. Sfakianakis and Mr. Karras.
Because something happened to him that touched his psyche.
What touched his psyche?
They say, maybe, his unrequited love for a young lady.
That young lady is showing herself in front of him and leads him to destruction.
To destruction?
To save himself he must drown her in the lake.
The young lady?
Yes. And if not her, any other woman.
But the women here are not afraid, right Archontoula?
Because...
Because?
Because Mr. Panos will drown the mother of his brother-in-law!
I'm at odds with myself!
He is awake! He is awake!
I'm at odds with myself for still loving you.
And my Ego is like trash on the street.
Antonis, have you been here long? Why didn't you wake us up?
So, that's how it is Mr. Panos, you want to drown my mother in the lake?
- What is he talking about?
- Why don't you drown yourself?
Leave us alone you redneck! You hick!
- ...to do something good for mankind.
Peloponnesian filth! We let you wander around and you steal the peoples bread!
Antonis, Panos knows nothing about drownings. Mr. Professor said those things.
- Who is that professor?
- Lecturer at the Washington University!
- Those guys could drive even a psychiatrist crazy.
Who am I to put up with them?
Can you tell me what exactly happened?
We passed his car as we were supposed to...
...but he has stopped in the meantime.
We get out and he says
"This where the historic Volvi summit was held."
And I tell him "I'm not really sure".
This guy is clueless about historical matters.
This is not where the summit was held.
Says who?! You?
Panos, in the Party they ask Panos
about historical matters.
Remember what Castanides said?
Antonis is PAOK's Paparigopoulos.
In 1979 in Cassandra, Chalkidiki...
...the second New Democracy summit was held.
Like we give a fuck.
Miday, on the 5th of March,
the Party youths had fish here.
After the meal...
...the then youth party member Vanggelis Meimarakis...
...read a proclamation.
The proclamation read that New Democracy...
...must transform itself from a
leader-based to a principle-based party.
This movement, known as the Volvi Movement...
...was to play a crucial role in future developments.
Hold on a second...
Didn't you say they stayed in Cassandra?
Yes, in Cassandra.
Then why did they eat here
and brought Volvi into the mix?
This hasn't been clarified.
You should have asked for an explanation.
Ask for an explanation?
But they are the same!
PASOK and New Democracy?!
Two faces of the same coin!
I feel sorry for you!
In Cassandra you piss, in Volvi you take the piss!
Every time we have a serious discussion,
you fuck it up!
- I fuck it up?!
- You!
And you mock Michails, who has made
a myriad sacrifices for you!
Can you give us like, one example?
When the police saw the video
and were looking to arrest you...
...didn't Michalis take your place
and say that he did it?
And they said "Are you kidding?"...
"It's obvious you are just pushing your
brother-in-law back, so that he doesn't throttle the referee!"
And he says "Yes, I am pushing him and so he has to keep balance by grabbing the referees neck".
- Was the ref payed off?
- Did he award you with two penalty shots?
Is it the refs fault
if you get scored on thrice?
- Was there a score reversal at the last minute?
- Three meters from the penalty box?!
Are you kidding me?
Manolas tackles Skartados...
...sends him airborne for three meters...
...and falls in the penatly box!
- He was faking it!
And the boy is lying half-dead in the mud,
and the refs shows him the yellow card...
...as if he is faking it? And he still has a heartbeat!?
As if we were waiting for the Laconian farmers
to come and teach us what a penalty is...
- Was it a penalty Mr. Panos?
- Miss, it was the definition of a penalty!
But Thessaloniki must install a customs office!
Where was your passport issued mister?
In Laconia? No entry!
No entry!
Antonis, I am afraid. Since the doctors said that
Myrto must be committed to the psychiatric hospital...
...he sits still in the smith shop for hours on end.
What happened with the girl?
We passed his car as we were supposed
to and he gets out of the Mercedes.
I tell him "Panos, stop".
Even I, who was not affected that much,
felt my knees getting weak on her sight.
- Was she really that beautiful?
- Beautiful?
I am telling you, she might not even be from this world.
And from which world was she?
I don't know...
God...
[SONG] I packed and I'm leaving the old one...
[SONG] ...I'm moving my love to a man from Thessaloniki
Panos! Leave the poor man be.
He is just as tortured as you are.
What are you talking about?
If I let "the tortured one" be,
we will have five extra mouths to feed.
It doesn't really look like anything serious.
Not serious?
Even I am struggling with women issues...
...and you think the redneck will get away with it?
Truth be told, you are quite the Don Juan, Panos.
See?
We'll get them Panos.
This guy has a kid in Germany and another one in Sweden.
If he gets close to a woman,
she is eating for two in no time.
You think that Clytemnestra is at risk as well?
Her? She will get knocked up by touching alone.
Antonis!
May we have a moment?
- Well?
- Well...
Like you said this morning...
...if we understood correctly...
...you proposed that we leave...
...go take care of the elderly...
...and take care of you momma as well...
- Correct.
- And you...
...tomorrow or, the latest the day after that, you board the ferry and come as well.
Exactly.
May I ask a question?
- Sure.
- Are you being serious?
It's just a friendly relationship, Panos.
Just a summertime friendship.
OK. So if you see her during
winter on Tsimiski street...
...you will take a left on Komninon street.
Well, no. I will say hello...
...what's new, and so on.
You might even sit and have a coffee?
Why not? We are friends after all.
Panos is asking if, beyond this
friendship there are any feelings?
Sure there are feelings. Man has feelings.
This is what seperates him from beast and plant.
There it is!
Let's make it clear then.
Are you in love?
Or are you just trying to tap-and-run her?
Antonis! Panos! Michalis!
Clytemnestra!
What do you mean "tap-and-run"?
Wasn't that part of PASOK 101?
Panos, leave PASOK out of this.
What does PASOK have to do with feelings?
Isn't he favored to lead?
If he makes it onto the MP list, of course.
And they didn't teach him the basics?
Is this how he is going to lead the people?
Well?
I took care of three families.
Now it's your turn.
We either go all or no one.
- No one!
Love that became fire...
...a lit cigarette...
...from your ashes yet again, I burn and die.
Love that became fire...
...a lit cigarette...
...from your ashes yet again, I burn and die.
Do we have a rope?
We do Panos, but what do we need it for?
To tie him up.
Who? Antonis?
I'll play nice to lure him in. You come from behind...
When I say the phrase "your momma".
Remember, "your momma"...
...you tie him up.
Tie up Antonis?
Who else?
There will be three wives waiting
and there is going to be only two of us?
- This is not good.
- Well?
When his wife asks you what you did
with her husband, what will you say?
That you left him with his mistress?
- Can you understand the issue you create?
- I create?
Well, who creates it then?
It's all "me, me, me".
Don't pick up.
It might be Antonis calling because he is feeling regret, Panos.
Eleni? We are starting in ten minutes.
We are missing for two days?
Here they say the had a summit
and try to fool everyone.
There was no summit.
But Antonis rebuked them and
it will become a political issue.
That joke of a man.
Panos...
Eleni asks if we want the veal with tomato
sauce or with baked potatoes.
Tomato sauce.
With tomato sauce and fried potatoes.
Make sure to fry a bunch.
Antonis wants a lot of popatoes.
As you know, he only eats the potatoes
and does not even touch the veal.
Alright...
I'll tie you up and deliver you to your wive like an Amazon package.
You joke of a man.
Follow them!
What do you see?
He is forcing her.
In broad daylight?!
- What "in broad daylight"?
- He is forcing her in broad daylight?
Is that what I just said?
"He is forcing her", that's what you said.
She does not want to eat a banana...
...and he is forcing her to eat a banana.
That's what I said!
She will gold-dig him for at least five hundred thousands.
Women in our age have their price, Panos.
You need at least fifteen just for drinks.
- Fifteen for one drink?
- Well, not one drink...
...but Vanggelis's girl drank three shots, going for a fourth...
...and he says "what do we owe?"...
...and orders three more shots on top of that.
The tab is at three thousand.
He pays and says "I'll go out and smoke".
She keeps on drinking. When dawn comes
she has no money to pay and is in trouble.
They ask "where is the guy who was with you?"...
And she says "I don't know, I just met him tonight"...
And thus Vanggelis got out of paying thirty thousand extra.
What was the point of this story?
Because Panos, I was thinking...
When Vaggelis was sick for thirty days...
...fifteen thousands divided by...
Panos! Michalis!
Clytemnestra! Antonis!
Follow them! Follow them!
Last we saw them in Olympiada.
In Arnea they told us they saw them having coffee.
Which means they didn't head to Hagion Oros.
- Great job Sherlock.
- We eliminiated one peninsula.
- Now it's your turn to choose.
- Did you choose?
I chose one out of three peninsulas.
Arnea...
Ormylia...
Nikiti...
Marmaras...
Porto Caras!
That joke of a man!
He thought he could escape me.
- Good evening.
- Hello.
Jack Daniels. Make one of them a double.
You fool. Can't you see how life is?
Become a minister to get the
dough and help us too.
We thought you will make it big...
...and we will live a better life
but you are running behind women.
Idiot...
Panos, who are you talking to?
Well then I will make it big on my own!
We will work. We have a lot of comissions.
Mr. Psomiadis said the other day "Be prepared for work..."
"...and in ten years the situation will be different."
I will make them suffer.
We don't want to harm anyone.
Bet everything on thirty-six red.
You don't mean, we will gamble, right?
We got to here and won't gamble?
We don't have money Panos.
If Antonis does not lend us we are in dire straights.
Next month we have to pay...
...two rents, insurance...
...phone and power bills. Income tax.
We have to buy raw metal. Clothes for the kids.
Stuff for the household.
Take a look at this miser.
Why are you reminding me of all this?
Do you know what I have been through?
- What happened to you?
- When we were coming I said...
...Panagiotis, if you see a dog on
a motorcycle, take it as a sign.
Did we or did we not see the sign?
I saw no sign, just a motorcycle
with four dogs running after it.
Well, motorcycle and dog, that was the sign.
Four dogs? Even better.
But why thirty-six red? We have no sign for that.
What was the weather like on St. Antons even
when we lit the forge?
- Snowstorm.
- Did the door open and you asked who it was?
I did Panos because I got scared...
...the door was loked from the inside, how did it open?
- Did we see a woman?
- She was tall and slim and...
...she ordered thirty-six candleholders.
Did she sign the check as "Joan Pappos, Nevada"?
- We cashed it.
- Did she ever come for the candleholders?
No, and we had to sell them.
Did they say that that night,
many saw the Holy Mother...
...and a lame guy got healed?
As did a woman in Kalamaria.
So?
Your bets please.
Why the hell are you betting everything on black? To jinx me?
To have a second out, Panos.
No more bets please.
Seventeen, black.
Répétition.
No more bets please.
Will you look at the imbecile betting on 36 red?
Not even we could pull this off.
36 red.
That's motherfucking it! I'm voting for PASOK!
Your bets please.
Even if I tell you Panos, you would not believe it.
Six times répétition for 36!
Like it was enchanted or something.
The croupier asked me if we are related to him.
I told him "He is our brother-in-law, Antonis". And he says...
"We haven't seen such a good player in ages."
You know why he said that?
Because he tipped the shit out of him.
No, Panos. I was in charge of tipping.
I pretended throwing them a chip...
...they said "Thank you"...
...and I put the chip back in my pocket.
We are broke, we can't tip.
Squeeze her tight you redneck.
But watch out for any dangerous swelling.
Panos, let them be.
Antonis saved us.
And Clytemnestra, could be the woman every man dreams of meeting once in his life.
You are payed off, right? He payed you to sweet-talk me.
Tell me, the rat saw the cheese, but did he see the trap?
What do you mean, Panos?
They let him win today, so that tomorrow he loses twice as much.
And the chick...
...once they suck him dry, she is gone.
Won't you eat your eggs?
That half-wit fuck boy.
We gathered you all here, stupid southerners...
...and you are stealing our bread.
Panos, I wonder...
...if this Ms. Joan Pappos comes back one day...
...and asks for the candleholders.
What did he tell you when you woke him up?
He says he will be down in half an hour. I leave, they ask for Mr. Arbouzoglou.
I pick up the phone again, he asks "did you have breakfast yet?"
I say, "no".
He says, "Get some and charge it to room 331".
Empty gestures like that are the shepherd's favorite.
Nevertheless, he thought about us, Panos.
Because, people who bask in their happiness usually don't think of others.
Tell me, do you remember the code-word?
Now, you think we mean you harm?
That we don't want you to enjoy yourself a bit?
That we are not your brothers-in-law?
Isn't it you who takes care of the elders and my sisters?
Isn't it you who pays for the study help for the kids?
- Didn't you go to the taxman...
- Didn't you go to the taxman to save us?
You told him...
"If those two poor souls..."
"...who work since they were twelve, neglected to VAT once or twice, are guilty..."
"...then half of Greece should be behind bars."
And he tells you "I am just doing my job".
And you tell him "PASOK came to teach you that you job is..."
"...to stand next to the people and solve their problems."
- And I go to the taxman...
...and he tells me "what a magnificent person that brother-in-law of yours."
"It is people like that who should govern us!" And I think to myself...
Antonis, I wish your mother was here to hear this...
...and rejoice, that poor woman.
Yes, but you vote for New Democracy.
That is indeed true.
Other party memebers say...
..."Not even your brothers-in-law vote for PASOK..."
"...and you dream of becoming MP?"
And you didn't flip them off?
Who told you this? I'll deck his face and teach him not to be ignorant.
They are being ignorant.
I'll tell him "Come here you ashole.."
"...Did you even ask why I have to vote for New Democracy?"
If Psomiadis told you "Cut the crap and vote for my grandson..."
"...because I put bread on your table and not PASOK", what would you do?
That, if he didn't work with you, two families would out in the street?
Relax, your blood pressure will spike again.
Let is spike! Let it reach 24, let me die right here in front of him!
Look how they divide us.
And Psomiades comes, elections eve...
...and brings some Touloubes and some sealed election sheets.
And I count the sheets and ask him "Mr. Vasilis..."
"...me, plus my wife, my father and my sister is four..."
"...plus Michails, his wife and his mother, that's seven..."
"...Why eight sheets?"
And he says "What about the mother of your in-law, Antonis."
So, my mother voted for New Democracy?
What were my options, Antonis?
I took her to the station, gave her the election sheet...
...and told her "Ms. Vasiliki, Antonis said to vote it."
She crossed herself, kissed it..
...corssed it as well thrice...
...and threw it in the ballot box!
Antonis, woohoo!
Clytemnestra, woohoo!
Antonis, look it's Clytemnestra. Woohoo!
Father...
Clytemnestra, help! Clytemnestra, help!
- Woe us.
- We came Mr. Michalis
...because Ms. Clytemnestra called us and told us where you are.
They throwing two families to the streets.
We hired a cab so that we can entertain you.
Help me.
The jacket! Take off his jacket!
Take it off.
Michalis!
Hang the jacket somewhere.
Let him get some air. Why did you do this to us Antonis?
Such good people...
...yet such a drama.
It has been a month.
The machines are gathering rust...
...and the children are cold and hungry.
Flyers are handed out in the streets of Athens.
Workers are asking for solidarity.
That which comes as an evolution in labor relations...
...could be something unknown...
...and beyond our comprehension.
Michalis!
The children of the future will grow up in a new reality...
...a reality, which we will propably never know.
Michalis!
I'm busy Panos.
In this critical moment, PASOK is the only party that can stand beside the people...
...and lead them to the threshold of this new world...
...without having to sink them into despair and marginalize them.
See?
We have never heard such nice words like that.
Who will tell them to us?
The Right is not discoursing in the level of ideas...
...but, stuck to the old mentality, they prefer to bribe the souls of the people.
Exactly!
In the meanwhile, us, you tell us to help with the elections...
...so, we ask "where do you want your child to be positioned in?"
Or, "Do you need a loan?", to keep the people happy.
Well done Mr. Panos!
Remember in Stavroupoli? You call us...
..."Come lift Venizelos up to the stage".
And when you got off the Mercedes me and Michalis picked him up...
...and it is since that day I have this backpain.
You sacrificed a lot.
But, how can I tell my father...
...that mother voted for New Democracy?
But Antonis, your father has been dead for 25 years.
He was an anti-authoritarian in Papaditsa.
He was drinking his coffee alone in the village square and then he came home.
His mother would say...
..."Giannis, don't despair that no one is saying hello to you."
"You forgive them."
When in 1982, on St. Johns day, his namesday, he came into my dream, I told him...
"Father..."
"...the blessed day has come!"
"The People now have the power in their hands!"
Mr. Antonis, we vote for New Democracy...
...but, now that we have heard the story of your dad...
...we will vote for PASOK.
Right Archontoula?
When I tell you he was not feeling well, you better believe me.
Yes, similar to the one Panos had but a bit less serious.
Now he is giving a speech.
Of course he is giving a speech, you never know when elections might pop up!
We start in half an hour.
If we are having the lamb, start with it now.
And we can reheat it if we arrive too late.
All right, Eleni.
Antonis, with Panos we will arrange for some quality fish.
I don't want fish.
What do you want?
Kokoretsi.
Kokoretsi?
Leave it up to me.
Panos, he does not want normal Kokoretsi, he wants it Papadits-style.
Papaditsa-style, of course. Leave it up to me I said.
I will become the step that will help you rise.
I will become your cry of passion.
You'll love me you'll see, you'll love me.
I will laugh for me. I will pay for me.
Because, until this day...
Two thousand one hundred seventy.
Two thousand one hundred eighty.
Two thousand one hundred ninety.
Two thousand two hundred.
Two thousand two hundred ten.
Two thousand two hundred twenty.
Two thousand two hundred thirty.
Two thousand two hundred forty.
Two thousand two hundred fifty.
...everything I did, I did for you.
That's enough.
Mister, still dirty.
Get done with it! I want them dirty goddammit!
Damn Albanians...
...we let you wander around and you steal the peoples bread!
You will eat the Papaditsa-style Kokoretsi to regain yourself.
And once you feel better, we start to meet our families.
What are you talking about? Did you ask him if he is in the state to travel?
I don't have any cash left.
It got wet.
We tried to save it Antonis, but the bills kept dissolving in our hands.
We will loan you some, and you give it back to us whenever you can.
But, you gambled all of it away.
We did. But we regained it. Some from non-tips, some from this, some from that.
- But, you owe me money.
- You will get it.
Panos says to now mess up the loans.
We owe you, you owe us...
...and whoever can will pay his share back.
So, you are leaving.
I must.
You must...
And I must learn to accept everything as it comes.
It is my fault...
...now that I hurt and cry alone...
...it is my fault.
"Stay, I want you, I love you"
I couldn't find the strength to say.
Now what can I say?
It is my fault.
Why shouldn't I stop you from leaving?
Stand at the door and not let you go.
Why shouldn't I call 911 and tell dispatch...
...that I won't make it.
That I won't make it.
Mr. Panos, congratulations!
I assure you that I have never eaten such a delicious kokoretsi.
Cheers to PAOK!
PAOK! PAOK! PAOK! PAOK! PAOK!
Why shouldn't I stop you from leaving?
You have had your fair share of women.
Why shouldn't I call 911 and tell dispatch...
...that I won't make it.
That I won't make it.
Why shouldn't I stop you from leaving?
Stand at the door and not let you go.
Why shouldn't I call 911 and tell dispatch...
...that I won't make it.
That I won't make it.
You failed Lothario...
So, you thought we don't love you?
But you are solid.
If you didn't just regurgitate all your speeches you would be top.
And we would also be top alongside you.
And the girl is top as well.
Top league.
PAOK.
But, will you leave four kids behind?
And Eleni and his mother too, Panos.
She is a girl of substance.
What substance?
We communicate, Panos.
That's what a woman is about?
No.
But a woman can love and give herself.
And her relationship to a man determines her destiny...
...which many times is unmerciful.
There it is again with the PASOK-speak,
so we can't decode what you are saying.
We'll live a life we can't imagine.
Fuck off.
What life?
When you get the permit from the party headquarters
and we open the betting house...
...our wives will make dough and not care about us.
- And is that good?
-Of course it is!
They will make a houndred grand a day.
- Pure income?
-Pure as a diamond!
- So we are going to divorce them?
-We will keep custody of the kids.
They can't forbid us from seeing our kids, Antonis!
When I woke up on Christmas Eve.
Eleni was sitting by the window.
I said "Good day" but she did not answer.
- She was crying.
Crying?
Yes. She was crying with sadness.
Then she went to the living room.
I followed her.
She took our kid's picture from cupboard
and was looking at it.
- Which picture?
From our kid that drowned.
That was fifteen years ago, Eleni was a girl back then.
Yes. And she said...
...if the ocean did not take it...
...we would be together, happy.
I had the same.
Christmas Eve and she starts with how I don't earn enough...
...and how the old perv is taking advantage of us.
And I start slapping her around...
...and make me a coffee and I see her...
...talking with your wife on the phone.
My wife didn't do anything out of the ordinary this Christmas.
And she calls me two days ago and she was acting all nice...
"Panos, when are you coming?"
We've been alone for a month.
Like she had a clue.
Doesn't matter.
Are they having a good time now?
Once we get there, are they going to annoy our balls off?
We just don't get it, Panos.
Doesn't matter.
Remember the woodcocklings that Matoula
and the old perv brought?
The ones we cooked in wax paper?
I do.
Matoula would take them out of the oven
and mouthfeed the old perv.
And we didn't get as much as a wing.
And she said, "My Koulis, the poor woodcocklings..."
"...came from Africa and didn't have
a clue about what awaits them".
He put everything away!
Didn't leave a feather.
Yes! Our fates will be the same as the woodcocklings!
I saw a tear in your eye...
...which you wipe away with dignity and pass me.
And when you reach the last step...
...you stop for a moment and look at me in silence.
It is your right to stay or leave.
You are answerable to no one.
Don't feel guilt for what you are leaving behind.
All our mistakes are mine.
It is your right to stay or leave.
You are answerable to no one.
Don't feel guilt for what you are leaving behind.
All our mistakes are mine.
Finally! It's noon!
I had to gather our things alone and it's still my fault!?
So, I'm not allowed to have back-pain this one time?
Must we fight?
I really don't get him sometimes...
Ms. Archontoula, Ms. Soultana, we will come and see you once a week at the least.
Panos, Antonis, right?
But of course.
Visit again Mr. Antonis! Visit again Mr. Panos!
- What is up?
- Why did we stop?
- Antonis did.
Michalis, we have to stay here a bit and recuperate.
And take a swim too.
So that we don't catch the heat in the ferry.
- And in the evening...
- What evening?
Before sunset we will be at Thasos.
Good idea and I agree, but I am worried that they will get worried.
- Who will get worried?
- Our families.
But, you will go and let them know we are coming.
How will they worry?
Wait a minute. So I go alone and you come later?
Yes, that's what we've been saying the whole time.
I, deflate the tires!
I, mix sugar into the gas!
I, forget my cigarette lit and everything burns to hell! That's what I do!
Why the fuck are you yelling?
Did you stare Death in his eyes, like me and Antonis?
I'm the fool!
Did you drop into the lake, with leeches suckling the blood out of you?
I'm the addlehead!
Did you get stuck in the mud, with water-snakes slithering up on you?
What am I, chopped liver?!
All three of us shall stay.
But, we will go swim only once.
We will eat something light.
We will take a nap.
And, as soon as the sun sets and it gets cooler...
...we leave for our families immediately.
This has been a labour of love, dedicated to the memory of the great Stavros Tsiolis.
Subs by ravingraven
Special thanks to /r/greececirclejerk, narkalieuths, sapounious, Dr. S.C, TEL2091
https://github.com/ravingraven/as_perimenoun_oi_gynaikes
Love each other.